this is the first video in a six part
series on yoga in this series I'll look
at the effect yoga may or may not have
on a wide variety of conditions and yes
to do a little myth busting but in both
directions
check it out
[Music]
the practice of yoga for health has
become popular in the United States and
worldwide a 2016 survey estimated that
36 million Americans may be involved in
yoga to varying degrees though the
origins of yoga go back thousands of
years it was only introduced in the
United States about a century ago what
are the risks and the benefits yoga
users tend to report having a better
health status but that doesn't
necessarily mean yoga was the cause for
example yoga practitioners were more
likely to be normal weight rather than
obese and that alone could give you
better health of course if the yoga was
responsible for the weight loss then
that would certainly be to yoga's credit
but yoga users are also more likely to
be white female young and college
educated all of which are independently
associated with better health status the
same thing with higher socioeconomic
status
yoga practitioners also tend to exhibit
other positive Health behaviors
specifically more regular physical
activity in general and a vegetarian
diet and the more yoga people practice
the more likely they were to cut out
meat and eat more and more fruits and
vegetables for every additional day per
week of yoga practice the odds of being
vegetarian increased 20 percent how
about one of three yoga teachers
surveyed in the UK follow a plant-based
diet much higher than the general
population
so when you're doing a study like this
comparing the cardiovascular health of
yoga practitioners to Runners to
sedentary individuals you can see how
difficult it would be to tease out the
effects of yoga when significantly more
yogis reported refraining from eating
meat compared to the other two groups
it's like when I was reading about the
role of yoga and the prevention and
management of various cardiovascular
diseases I was so excited to read that
yoga could significantly reduce
cholesterol levels after all heart
disease the number one killer of men and
women and when I looked at those studies
I got really excited reversal of
coronary atherosclerosis with yoga I
thought the only lifestyle intervention
that could reliably do that was a whole
food plant-based diet well why do you
think the yoga lifestyle intervention
was a diet packed so full of whole plant
Foods fruits vegetables whole grains
beans and nuts they were getting about
50 grams of fiber a day no wonder they
got heart disease reversal but what role
if any did the yoga itself actually play
now if yoga gets you to adopt a better
lifestyle stop smoking eat healthier
great Whatever Gets people to take
better care of themselves right if your
tin foil hat tells you martians want you
to skip the donuts I'm all in favor
whatever it takes but if we are to tease
out whether practicing yoga has any
special benefits in and of itself we
really need to look at Interventional
studies or randomized control tries that
go beyond just associations and
correlations and can instead prove cause
and effect for example when we find yoga
users have better health status and are
less likely to be obese that could be
reverse causation meaning instead of
yoga leading to Better Health than a
normal weight maybe being in Better
Health not being obese is leading to
more yoga same with the flip side when
you read that yoga practitioners are
more likely to have mental health
conditions depression anxiety
musculoskeletal conditions like
arthritis gout lupus fibromyalgia paint
sprains and Asthma yeah maybe yoga could
be contributing to some of those
conditions like muscle sprains but for
most of these it's probably reverse
causation right people with diseases
seeking help
are they getting it the only way to know
for sure is to put it to the test which
we'll explore next
[Music]